Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
JW Broadcastingへようこそ！
This month we’ll consider
ways we can get
今月は 聖書の原則から
最大限の益を得る方法について考えます
the most benefit
from Bible principles.
Here are some highlights:
ハイライトをご覧ください
How can Bible study and meditation
聖書の研究と黙想は わたしたちを
どのように試みに備えさせますか？
prepare us for trials?
We’ll learn about the example
of Sister Gertrud Pötzinger
アーカイブを通して—
ゲルトルート･ポエツィンガー姉妹の
経験から学びましょう
through an archived interview.
What principles and Bible accounts
enabled her and her husband, Martin,
ドイツのナチス政権下にあっても
どんな聖書の原則や記述が—
to keep their integrity
in Nazi Germany?
ポエツィンガー兄弟姉妹を
力づけたでしょうか？
Jehovah urges us
to seek first the Kingdom.
エホバは王国を第一にするよう
求めておられます
What can happen when a person
seeks things in the world
王国ではなく 世のことに気を取られると
どうなるでしょうか？
instead of the Kingdom?
We’ll listen to how this young sister
learned to trust Jehovah
若い姉妹がどのように
エホバを信頼するようになり—
人生の真の幸福を見つけたか
見てみましょう
and lead a life that brings
true happiness.
Have you ever thought
that a familiar piece of Bible counsel
何度も聞いたことがある
聖書の原則の場合—
didn’t apply to your situation?
自分には当てはまらないと
考えることがありますか？
Well, how can analyzing such counsel
lead to related principles
特定の状況にあった原則を
導き出すため—
that fit your specific challenge?
聖書の教えを
どのように分析できますか？
We’ll see
in this encouraging dramatization.
励みあるドラマから学びましょう
You’re watching
JW Broadcasting for February 2017.
それでは 2017年2月の
JW Broadcastingです！
You and I make a lot of decisions every day.
わたしたちは毎日
たくさんの決定をします
Now, some have a little impact on our lives;
小さな決定もあれば
大きな決定もあります
others have a very big impact.
And we can appreciate that we can make
自分で選択し
決定できることに感謝できます
choices and decisions for ourselves.
もし自分で決定できないとしたら
と考えてみてください
Think of how life would be
if you made no decisions for yourself
—someone tells you when to go to bed,
いつ寝るか 何を着るか
どんな仕事をするかを—
they pick out your clothes,
だれかに決められる
としたらどうでしょう？
and they tell you what to do for work.
だれもそうなりたいとは思いません！
Well, none of us would like that!
Jehovah gave each of us free will,
エホバは自分で決定ができるよう—
自由意志という素晴らしい贈り物を
与えてくださいました
and that’s the precious gift
of making choices for ourselves.
エホバがこの贈り物を与えてくださった
理由を考えたことがありますか？
Now, have you ever thought
about why Jehovah gave us this gift?
I mean,
why trust us with free will
わたしたちが時に良くない選択や
決定をしてしまうのに—
when he knew that we could make
bad choices or decisions?
わたしたちを信頼して
与えてくださったのはなぜでしょう？
Well, one powerful reason is love.
1つの大切な理由は 愛です
The only way to give us the gift of love
わたしたちに愛を贈る唯一の手段が
自由意志という贈り物なのです
is also to give us the gift of free will.
The two are tied together.
この2つは密接に関連しています
You really can’t have
one without the other.
片方だけでは成り立ちません
例えば わたしが自分に
“ジョン 愛しています”
For example,
if I programmed my computer
to give me a message
every day at 2:00 p.m.:
“あなたは素晴らしい人です”
というメールを—
“John, I love you.
I think you’re a wonderful guy,”
毎日午後2時に送るよう
セットしたとします
I think there’d be a little something
wrong with me if I thought:
それを見て “ああ ありがたい”
“コンピューターがわたしを愛している”
とは考えません
‘Aw, isn’t that nice?
My computer, it loves me.’
Yeah, love only exists
そうです 愛とは自由意志からのみ
出てくるものなのです
if it comes truly
from a free-will expression.
Now, did Jehovah place
any boundaries on free will?
では エホバは自由意志に
制限を設けられましたか？
Yes.
はい そのことをイスラエル国民への
律法の中に記されました
They were stated in the Law
to the nation of Israel.
And Jesus later repeated them
後にイエスは マタイ 22章37-40節で
そのことに言及されました
at Matthew 22:37-40:
“He said to him:
“イエスは彼に言われた
「『あなたは 心をこめ 魂をこめ—”
“‘“You must love Jehovah your God
with your whole heart
“思いをこめてあなたの神
エホバを愛さねばならない』”
“‘“and with your whole soul
and with your whole mind.”
“‘This is the greatest
and first commandment.
“これが最大で第一のおきてです”
“第二もそれと同様であって こうです”
“‘The second, like it, is this:
“‘“You must love your
neighbor as yourself.”
“『あなたは隣人を自分自身のように
愛さねばならない』”
“‘On these two commandments
“律法全体はこの二つのおきてに
かかっており—”
the whole Law hangs,
and the Prophets.’”
“預言者たちもまたそうです」”
So our use of free will
わたしたちの自由意志は—
神と隣人への愛という境界内で
示されるべきです
has love of God
and love of neighbor
as its boundaries.
Notice, for example,
例えば この絵の中で—
what people are doing
in this picture,
円の境界内にいる人と
外にいる人との違いに注目してください
both inside the circle boundary
and outside.
See, free will allows us to do
自由意志を用いて
絵の中にいる人は何でもできます
any of the things
we see in the picture.
But love of God
and love of neighbor
しかし 神と隣人への愛は
わたしたちを円の外にいる人から遠ざけ—
move us to reject
what’s outside the circle
and choose
to do the kinds of things
円の中にいる人に
良いことを行なうよう動かします
that we see inside the circle.
Now, to stay
within those boundaries,
円の中にいるために エホバは貴重な
知力と良心を与えてくださいましたが—
Jehovah gave us
a marvelous brain
and a built-in conscience,
同時に助けが必要であることも
ご存じです
but he also knows
we need more help.
And that’s why
he also gave us Bible principles
だからこそ エホバは聖書の原則を与えて
その基本的な真理によって—
—basic truths from the Bible
that can help us
to make good decisions.
良い決定ができるように
してくださいました
And it can safely be said
that any decision we face
それで どんな決定も
聖書の原則を導きにできるのです
can be guided
by Bible principles.
Now, our Creator, Jehovah,
knows what’s best for us.
創造者エホバは何が最善かをご存じです
And he also trusts us
to make decisions
わたしたちが聖書の原則によって決定すると
信頼してくださっています
based on Bible principles
because he knows
that when we do that,
そうするなら
わたしたちが幸福になり 満足し—
then we’re really,
truly going to be happy, content,
神と隣人との平和な関係を
楽しめることをご存じなのです
and at peace with him
and with others.
So in review so far:
振り返ってみましょう
Jehovah gave us free will
エホバは自由意志を
与えてくださいました
—that’s the privilege
to make choices for ourselves—
それは 決定をする上での貴重な贈り物です
and he also gave us
Bible principles
また 決定に制限を設けるため
聖書の原則も与えてくださいました
as the boundaries
to our choices.
But making difficult decisions
requires that we train ourselves
難しい決定をする時には—
特に聖書の原則を認め
当てはめなければなりません
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
Now let’s read Romans 12:1,
ローマ 12章1節を読んで—
and let’s see how this verse
決定することに関して
何と述べているか考えてみましょう
describes the decision-making process.
“Therefore, I appeal to you
“そのようなわけで 兄弟たち—”
“わたしは神の情けによってあなた方に懇願します”
“by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“あなた方の体を神に受け入れられる—”
“holy and acceptable to God,
“生きた 聖なる犠牲として差し出しなさい”
a sacred service
with your power of reason.”
“これがあなた方の理性による神聖な奉仕です”
So are we using
our “power of reason”
聖書の原則を理解するため
“理性”を働かせていますか？
to understand Bible principles?
For example, young children
例えば
子どもはたくさんの質問をします
ask lots of questions.
But has a child ever asked you:
でも こう聞いたりするでしょうか？
“What happens when I drop a ball?
“ボールを離したらどうなるの？
ペンは？本は？”
a pencil? a book?”
No, they don’t ask that.
そんなことはしません
They know what happens
to anything they drop.
物を離したらどうなるかは
分かっています
It falls down!
当然落ちます！
See, the child doesn’t need
rules for every object
子どもは原則を理解したなら
規則など必要とはしません
but has quickly grasped the principle.
Anything he drops falls down.
手から放した物は落ちます
では 18歳の子が
“このペンを離したらどうなるの？”—
Now,
what if an 18-year-old asked you,
“What’s going to happen
when I drop this pen?”
と聞いたならどうでしょうか？
Well, it’s obvious
he’s not been paying attention
明らかに物理の基本原則を
理解していないことになります
to basic principles of life.
So by us paying attention
to Bible principles,
聖書の原則に注意を払うなら—
we can very quickly see
the pattern
長い規則集など必要とせずに
正しいことを見分け—
of love of God
and love of neighbor
神と隣人への愛を示す方法を
すぐに見極めることができます
and know
the right thing to do
without a long list of rules
for every situation.
Well, how can we train
our “power of reason”?
では どのように
“理性”を働かせますか？
We train it by paying attention
聖書を注意深く読み
研究することによってそうできます
as we read and study the Bible.
Now, we don’t need rules
どんな映画を観るか
どんな音楽を聴くか—
for which movies to watch,
which songs to listen to,
何を着るかに関して
規則は必要ありません
or what clothes we can wear.
If we’re paying attention
when we’re reading the Bible,
聖書を注意深く読むなら
聖書の原則によって良心を訓練し—
we train our conscience
with Bible principles
規則集なしに良い決定を
することができます
so we can make
such decisions
without needing
a long list of rules.
You know,
we could compare our training
“理性”を働かせることを
盲導犬と比較することができます
of our “power of reason”
to a blind person
using a guide dog.
Now, an untrained dog
特に訓練されていない犬でも
視覚障害者にとって助けになります
would be very helpful
to a blind person.
It would bark when others
were around, for example.
例えば 何かがあれば吠えるでしょう
However,
a dog trained
しかし 特別に訓練された盲動犬は
驚くほど有能です
in specific skills
is amazingly helpful.
The dog knows
when to stop at curbs
曲がり角の前で止まったり—
and walk around obstacles
人がぶつからないよう
障害物を避けることもします
that the person
might run their head into.
A guide dog
is also taught a skill called
盲導犬は“賢い不服従”と呼ばれる
特殊な訓練も受けます
“intelligent disobedience.”
And even if the blind person
encourages the dog forward,
視覚障害者が進もうと促しても従わず
危険を避けようとします
it won’t obey,
but it’ll pull
the person back from danger.
Now, it can take a year or more
of training for the dog to learn
盲導犬がそのように有能になるには
1年かそれ以上の時間が必要です
the amazing skills
that are so helpful to a blind person.
Likewise, our raw,
untrained “power of reason”
同様に 訓練されていない“理性”も
幾らか助けにはなります
can help us to a degree.
However, it can be amazing
しかし 時間をかけて訓練するなら
驚くべき働きをします
if we take the time to train it.
Now, here are
three skills that we can use
では “理性”を訓練するのに役立つ
3つのスキルを考えましょう
to train our “power of reason.”
They are illustrating,
例える 分析する バランスを取るです
analyzing,
and balancing.
Now, to consider our first skill,
illustrating,
最初のスキル 例えることについて
人を許すというトピックで考えましょう
let’s use the general topic
of forgiveness.
What Bible principles
could help with forgiveness?
どんな聖書の原則によって
他の人を許すよう助けられますか？
できるだけたくさんの原則や聖句を
思い浮かべてみてください
Please think of as many principles
and scriptures as you can.
Now, if it helps,
you can pause the program now
そして よければビデオをいったん止め—
思い浮かんだ原則を
書き出してみましょう
and write down
the principles that come to mind.
Now, your list
may include principles like these:
その中には マタイ 18章22節の
“77回まで”許しなさい や—
Matthew 18:22 says
to forgive “up to 77 times”;
Proverbs 12:18 says:
箴言 12章18節の
“賢い者たちの舌は人をいやす”—
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”;
and Colossians 3:13 tells us
コロサイ 3章13節の“惜しみなく
許し合いなさい”などがあるでしょう
to ‘forgive one another freely.’
Now, the skill
we want to learn is illustrating
今 学んでいるのは例えること—
—creating a mental picture
of an idea or principle
つまり 心の中で聖句の考えや原則の
真の意味と要点を思い浮かべる能力です
to see its real meaning
and impact.
Now, even if we
are not skilled artists,
芸術家ではなくても わたしたちは皆
心の中で思い描くことができます
all of us can and do create
pictures in our minds.
When illustrating,
pay attention to things that are similar
例えを考えるとき 同じものあるいは
似たものにするよう心がけてください
or like the thing
you are trying to visualize.
For example,
if sin is like debt,
例えば 罪が借金であれば
許しはそれを帳消しにするものです
then forgiveness
is like someone canceling the debt.
If a hurtful remark
is like a cut,
感情を傷つけることが
皮膚を切ることならば—
then forgiveness
is like seeing it heal.
許しはそれを治療することです
If sin is like a mark
on a blackboard,
罪が黒板に線を引くことなら
許しはそれを消すことです
forgiveness is like erasing it.
Proverbs 12:18
箴言 12章18節は
例えに関しての良い手本です
is a great example
of using the “like” technique.
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
“剣で突き刺すかのように
無思慮に話す者がいる”
but the tongue of the wise
is a healing.”
“しかし 賢い者たちの舌は人をいやす”
Imagine what your skin
would look like
幼いころ傷つけ 出血した所が
今どうなっているか考えてみてください
if you still had
every open cut, bruise,
or bleeding scratch
since childhood.
See, Jehovah
wonderfully designed our body
エホバは自然治癒力という
素晴らしい力を与えてくださいました
to heal such minor cuts
and bruises.
And we can now visualize
how the forgiveness of others
人を許すことによって
感情的に立ち直っていく様を想像できます
helps us to heal emotionally.
Now, learning to illustrate,
or visualize,
では 例えや想像力を
時間をかけて訓練しましょう
takes time and practice.
However, it can be one
of the most powerful skills we use
それは“理性”を働かせることができる
最も強力なスキルの一つです
to train
our “power of reason,”
and it can also be
quite enjoyable.
それは楽しいものとなります
You know,
try at your family worship
家族の崇拝で
一つのトピックから原則を考え—
to take
the principles for a topic
and see
how many similarities,
どれだけ多くの例えや類似点が
思いつくか—
or “likes,”
you can come up with.
やってみるのはいかがでしょう？
Now, granted,
they all won’t be amazing,
それらを発表し合うなら 新たな観点を
発見できて驚かされるかもしれません
but you may be surprised
by the insights
that come from seeing
something from a new perspective.
Well, let’s consider now
our second skill:
では次に 2つ目のスキル
分析することについて考えましょう
analyzing.
Now, analyzing something means
分析するとは—
あるものを“細かいところまで
注意深く調べる”ことです
“examining it carefully in detail.”
And let’s use
the topic of wrong desires.
これを間違った欲望という
トピックで考えてみましょう
Now, in this case,
let’s say that we’ve already found
コロサイ 3章5節の原則について
取り上げてみます
the principle
at Colossians 3:5:
“Deaden, therefore, your body members
that are on the earth
“ですから 淫行 汚れ
性的欲情 有害な欲望—”
“as respects sexual immorality,
uncleanness,
“また強欲
つまり偶像礼拝に関して—”
“uncontrolled sexual passion,
“hurtful desire, and greediness,
“地上にあるあなた方の肢体を
死んだものとしなさい”
which is idolatry.”
Now, what can we learn
from analyzing Colossians 3:5
悪い欲望と闘うよう—
コロサイ 3章5節を分析することから
何を学べますか？
to help when we struggle
with wrong desires?
Again, feel free
to pause the program
こうしたことを考えるために
再びビデオを止めてみてください
if you want some time
to think about it.
Look carefully
at each step outlined.
それぞれの段階を注意深く調べましょう
Did you notice, for example,
what appears to be
罪に至る段階に
どんなことがあるのかお気づきですか？
a reverse order
of the steps leading to sin?
This verse works its way
from sexual immorality
この聖句は淫行に至る
根本原因を明らかにしています
back to the very roots
of the problem.
Now, let’s take each phrase
starting with the last,
最後の文から考えましょう
“greediness, which is idolatry.”
“強欲つまり偶像礼拝”
So, sexual immorality
starts with selfishness,
淫行は自己本位 他の何よりも自分の必要に
貪欲であることから始まります
greedily putting our needs
ahead of anything else.
Next is “hurtful desire.”
次は “有害な欲望”です
Greediness leads to “hurtful desire.”
“強欲”は“有害な欲望”に至ります
It’s like a person
hanging around a bakery,
お金を払えないのに
パン屋の周りで—
smelling the bread and cakes
when he can’t pay for it.
パンやケーキの匂いを
嗅ぐことに似ています
Likewise,
hanging around immoral entertainment
同様に不道徳な娯楽や悪い交わりは—
or bad associates
わたしたちが本来持たないような
“有害な欲望”をかきたてます
can feed “hurtful desire”
for what is not ours.
Next is listed
“uncontrolled sexual passion.”
次は “性的欲望”です
So “hurtful desire”
has now turned from an idea
“有害な欲望”は それを満たすことが
できる機会を探すよう—
into a strong emotion
of passion,
強い感情的な欲望に変わります
causing one
to look for an opportunity
to fulfill the desire.
Next, “uncleanness.”
続いて “汚れ”
The previous steps have now led
to inappropriate physical conduct
この段階で
他の人との不適切な関係に至ります
with another person.
Finally, “sexual immorality”
—serious sin.
最後に重大な罪である“淫行”です
Sexual immorality
has occurred between persons
淫行は結婚関係外で起こります
that are not married
to one another.
So analyzing Colossians 3:5
コロサイ 3章5節を分析して—
悪い欲望を育てるのではなく
除くよう助けられます
can really help us to eliminate,
not stimulate, wrong desires.
And we can see
how important it is
それをすぐに捨て去ることの
重要性も分かります
to get rid
of wrong desires immediately.
It’s easier
to walk away from sin
前の段階であればあるほど
罪から離れるのは容易になります
when we’re still in the early stages,
rather than later.
So we need
to practice the skill
of not simply
just reading scriptures
聖句をただ読むのではなく
学んだことを生かして分析しましょう
but analyzing them
たくさんの調査用の道具を用いて—
until we’ve learned
all that we can.
And we can use
the many research tools we have
役立ちそうなコメントや適用を
見つけることができます
to find valuable comments
and application.
Now, let’s consider our third
では 最後の3つ目のスキルを
考えましょう
and final skill: balancing.
バランスを取る です
And to do that,
アルコールの用い方という
トピックで考えましょう
let’s use a question
on the topic of alcohol.
What Bible principles
could help a couple to decide
結婚する2人が披露宴で
アルコールを出すかどうかを決める際—
whether to serve alcohol
at their wedding?
どんな聖書の原則が役立ちますか？
What principles and scriptures
do you think would help them
バランスの取れた決定をするため
どんな聖句や原則を思い浮かべますか？
make a balanced decision?
Again, you’re welcome
to pause the program
再びビデオを止め 思い浮かんだ原則や
調べた点を書き出してみましょう
if you’d like to write down
what comes to mind
or to research something.
Now, your list probably has
some of these principles.
挙げられた原則は
次のようなものかもしれません
At John 2:9,
Jesus made wine for a wedding.
ヨハネ 2章9節でイエスが
水をぶどう酒に変えられたことです
However,
1 Corinthians 6:10 says
しかし コリント第一 6章10節には—
that ‘drunkards
will not inherit the Kingdom.’
“大酒飲みは神の王国を受け継がない”
ともあります
And 1 Corinthians 10:31, 32 says:
また コリント第一 10章31, 32節には—
“Whether you are eating or drinking . . . ,
“食べるにしても 飲むにしても—”
do all things for God’s glory”
“すべての事を
神の栄光のためにしなさい”
and to “keep from becoming
causes for stumbling.”
“つまずきのもととならないように”
ともあります
Now,
it doesn’t seem
たった1つの原則からは
答えを引き出すことはできないようです
that any one principle
provides the answer.
The couple could simply say:
2人は “イエスがそうされたんだから—”
“Well, Jesus served wine at a wedding,
so we can too.”
“披露宴でアルコールを出してもよい”
と言うかもしれません
However, there’s really more
to it than that, isn’t there?
しかし 本当にそれだけでしょうか？
It’s clear that a balance
バランスを取って
すべての原則を考えることが必要です
of all these Bible principles
is needed.
Will relatives
or others be there
出席者の中に
酩酊しやすい人がいますか？
who might be prone
to overdrinking?
Would serving alcohol bother
the conscience of many present
地元の習慣や考え方により
兄弟たちの良心が異なりますか？
because of local customs
and feelings about alcohol?
It’s often the case
when making decisions
決定を下す時は幾つかの原則について
バランスを取って考えて—
that we need to balance
several Bible principles,
自分に有利な1つの原則だけで
決定してはなりません
not taking any one principle solely
on its own merit.
Jehovah expects us
to use our “power of reason”
エホバはわたしたちが
“理性”を働かせ—
バランスを取って原則を考えて
決定するよう望んでおられます
to balance Bible principles
and make good decisions.
Ecclesiastes 7:16-18
バランスに関して
伝道の書 7章16-18節は—
良い教訓を与えています
gives us good advice
about being balanced.
“Do not be overly righteous,
“義に過ぎる者となってはならない”
“また 自分を過度に
賢い者としてはならない”
“nor show yourself excessively wise.
“どうして自分の身に
荒廃をもたらしてよいであろうか”
“Why should you bring ruin to yourself?
“邪悪に過ぎる者であってはならない”
“Do not be excessively wicked,
nor be foolish.
“また 愚かな者となるな”
“Why should you die before your time?
“自分の時でもないのに
どうして死んでよいであろうか”
“It is best to grasp one warning
“一方をつかむことのほうが良いが
他方からも手を引くな”
“without letting go of the other;
for the one who fears God
will heed them both.”
“神を恐れる者は
それらすべてと共に出て行くからである”
How true.
真理ですね
Such balance between extremes
is often necessary
聖書の原則を当てはめる時—
対照的な2つの間で
バランスを取る必要があります
when we apply
Bible principles.
We need to heed them both,
so to speak.
いわば 両者に注意を払います
We need to balance
all the Bible principles
神と隣人への愛を示す決定をするため—
so we can come
to the decision
全ての聖書の原則のバランスを取る
必要があります
that would show love of God
and love of neighbor.
We could illustrate the balance
between different Bible principles
異なる原則に関して
バランスを取る点で—
この自転車の模型を使って考えましょう
and applying them with this model bike.
マラウイの兄弟から頂いた物です
It was a gift from a brother in Malawi.
Now, a bicycle has
three basic principles of operation:
自転車は3つの基本要素から
なっています
the brakes, the pedals, and the steering.
ブレーキ ペダル ハンドルです
Now, the brakes are really like principles
ブレーキは わたしたちが悪い方向へ
向かうのを食い止める原則のようです
that slow us down
or stop us from doing the wrong thing.
And the pedals are really like the principles
ペダルは神と兄弟姉妹への愛を示すよう
わたしたちを動かす原則のようです
that move us forward
in showing love for Jehovah
and our brothers and sisters.
And the steering is like our free will
ハンドルは エホバを歓ばせる決定を選ぶ
自由意志のようです
to choose a direction in life
that pleases Jehovah.
So making decisions
is like riding a bicycle.
決定は自転車に乗るのに似ています
We have to balance
several Bible principles.
幾つかの聖書の原則を
バランスを取って考えなければなりません
So in review,
振り返ってみましょう
Jehovah gave us free will
エホバは神と隣人への愛という範囲内で
用いられる自由意志と—
to use within the boundaries
of love of God and love of neighbor
and many other fine Bible principles.
多くの聖書の原則を
与えてくださいました
Making difficult decisions requires
that we train our “power of reason”
難しい決定をするときには
“理性”を働かせ—
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
原則を考え 適用しましょう
And we discussed
how to train
理性を働かせるのに役立つ
3つのスキルとは何でしたか？
our power of reason
with the three skills:
illustrating,
例える 分析する バランスを取る です
analyzing,
and balancing.
So no matter what decisions
you are faced with,
どんなことに直面するとしても—
we encourage you:
“聖書の原則によって導かれるように”
していきましょう
“Let Bible principles guide you.”
Let’s use
the following dramatization
続くドラマを見て ここまで
お話ししたことをさらに深めましょう
to practice the skills
we’ve just discussed.
In this video,
ビデオの中で 3人の兄弟姉妹が—
three Witnesses all hear
the same familiar Bible counsel
集会でお馴染みの聖書の原則が
話されるのを聞いています
at a Christian meeting.
And at first,
it doesn’t seem to apply
最初 今の自分たちには当てはまらない
と考えているようですが—
to anything
they’re currently experiencing,
but it does.
それは間違いです
Maybe that’s happened to you.
これはあなたにも起こり得ることです
As you listen to their reasoning,
彼らの心の声を聴き
良い決定をするために—
what do you think they
could do to let Bible principles
どのように聖書の原則を用いるか
見てみましょう
guide them
to making a good decision?
We must know Jehovah well.
エホバをよく知ることは大切です
That means knowing
his thinking on matters.
エホバの考えを知るため—
We should welcome
such an examination
調べ 必要なら調整しましょう
and make any necessary changes.
例として コリント第一 15章33節を
読みたいと思います
For example,
let’s read
1 Corinthians 15:33 together.
Here we read:
“惑わされてはなりません”
“Do not be misled.
“悪い交わりは
有益な習慣を損なうのです”
Bad associations spoil useful habits.”
As familiar as that principle is,
よく知っている原則です
では この原則を当てはめるのを
難しく感じている分野がありますか？
can you think of an area in your life
where it’s difficult to apply?
Hey, John.
ジョン
Hey.
I know it’s not your usual,
—はい
—いつもと違うんだけど—
but there’s no one to entertain
those clients tonight.
接待の仕事 夜やってくれるよな？
So can you do it?
Thanks.
—あの……
—よろしく！
But I have. . .
Great.
Until then,
it wasn’t my usual thing.
引き受けてしまった……あの時から
But I need to support my family.
でも 家族のためだ
And these aren’t really my friends.
まぁ それに ただの付き合いだし……
I can handle it.
何とかなる
I think.
そうだよな
. . .we’re faced with bad associations
……良くない交わりに
気づいていないこともあります
in subtle ways.
This may require us
to ask additional questions
こう考えてみましょう
of ourselves.
SNSで良くない交わりをして
いないだろうか？
Are we letting in bad association
もしかすると 別の形での良くない交わりに
気づくかもしれません……
through social media?
Perhaps we can think
of another way bad association. . .
I don’t think so
大丈夫と思う
—except for some friends
from my old congregation.
けど 前の会衆の友達はちょっと
Wow!
うわー 霊的に大丈夫？
They’re not doing so well spiritually.
But if I stay connected
and see what they’re doing,
でも 登録しといて
何してるか分かってたら—
maybe I can help them.
—助けになれるかも
—……影響を受けます
. . .can affect us.
Maybe it’s something very specific.
はっきり分かるものもあるでしょう
Or maybe
しかし 予想もしないところで—
bad association
is coming from a place
良くない交わりをしていることが
あるかもしれません
we never expected.
I only join games
with Witness friends I know.
ゲームしてるんだ
エホバの証人の友達とね
But sometimes
でも 時々—
they connect
with people I don’t know
知らない人が一緒にやってるんだよな
who pick games
I’m not sure we should play.
大丈夫なのかな？
But maybe my friends know them,
まぁ みんな知ってるんだろう
so they’re probably OK.
多分 大丈夫だ
It is vital that we avoid
bad associations.
良くない交わりを避けることは
とても重要なことです
Now,
as we resume in Psalm 26. . .
詩編 26編に戻りましょう……
The basic principle in this story
is one we all know:
ビデオで話された原則は—
“悪い交わりは有益な習慣を損なう”
というよく知られたものです
“Bad associations spoil useful habits.”
But do our three friends
find themselves in the same situation,
3人は 自分たちが—
コリント第一 15章33節を適用できる
状況にいると考えていましたか？
where they can simply apply
1 Corinthians 15:33
in exactly the same way?
No.
いいえ 家族の頭は
家族を支えることを気にかけていました
The family head is concerned
about supporting his family.
Our sister wants
to stay in touch with her friends
姉妹は 友達を霊的に助けたいと思い
連絡を取り続けました
in hopes of helping them spiritually.
And our young brother
didn’t know exactly who
若い兄弟はどんな人がゲームに
加わっているのか知りませんでした
his associates were.
Are you already thinking of
additional principles
では それぞれの状況で適用できる—
さらにどんな聖書の原則が
思い浮かびますか？
that would apply
to each person’s problem?
How would you illustrate, analyze,
or balance those principles
自分が同じ状況におかれたなら—
どのようにそれぞれの原則を例えて
分析し バランスを取りますか？
if you were in their position?
If you want to,
pause the program here.
よろしければビデオをいったん止め
考えたことを書き出してみましょう
Take the time to write down
what you’re thinking.
Then watch how they each
search for Bible principles
それから—
3人がどのように聖書の原則を調べ
“理性”を働かせるか見てみましょう
and train their “power of reason.”
I thought that talk
didn’t apply to me.
自分は大丈夫って思ってたけど
ほんとに大丈夫か？
But can I really handle
bad association?
If I take a stand,
I may lose my job.
断わったら 多分首だな
あぁ 明日のことを心配してるんだ
But that’s being anxious
about tomorrow.
Jesus said:
イエスは言ってた
“それで 思い煩って—”
“So never be anxious and say,
“ 「わたしたちは何を食べるのか」
「何を飲むのか」—”
“‘What are we to eat?’ or,
“‘What are we to drink?’ or,
“「何を身に着けるのか」などと
言ってはなりません”
‘What are we to wear?’”
Jehovah knows I need a job.
エホバは 仕事のことも
ちゃんと分かってる
And I need
to set a good example
それに 子どもたちも
わたしをよく見てるんだ
for when my children
face bad association.
1 Corinthians 15:33.
コリント第一 15章33節
My friends’ posts
are getting worse
写真もコメントも
どんどん良くない投稿になってる
—their pictures and comments.
Hmm, 2 Timothy 2:16.
うーん テモテ第二 2章16節
“But reject empty speeches
“また 聖なる事柄を汚す
むだ話からは遠ざかりなさい”
“that violate what is holy,
for they will lead
to more and more ungodliness.”
“そうした者たちは
いっそうの不敬虔へと進み ”
I’m letting them share
“empty speeches” with me online.
わたし ネット上で
“むだ話”をしてるんだ
I will try to help
them while I still can,
友達を助けたい
でも SNSでフォローするんじゃない
but following their posts
is not the way to do it.
やり方が違う
I told Mom what’s been happening
when I game
ゲームのことを母親に話してみた
with my friends.
She gave me good ideas
on what to look for
そしたら 「リサーチガイド」を
見てみたら って言ってくれた
in the Research Guide.
“Christian Life.”
「クリスチャン生活」
“Association.”
「交友」
“Is Your Recreation Beneficial?”
「益となるレクリエーションを
選んでいますか」
“Who Are My Companions?”
「だれと行なうか」
It says,
「気晴らしをだれと一緒にしたいと
思っているか」
“Who are the ones I want
to share my leisure time with?”
“Does he have the same Bible-based
values and morals that I have?”
“わたしと同じように 聖書に基づく
価値観や道徳観を持っているだろうか？”
Good question.
I don’t even know
who they are sometimes.
全然知らない人とゲームしてた
Psalm 119:63 says:
詩編 119編63節
“わたしは あなたを真に恐れる
すべての者たちの—”
“I am a friend of all who fear you
and of those who keep your orders.”
“また あなたの命令を
守る者たちの仲間なのです”
But if I only know them online,
ネットだけじゃ 本当にエホバを
敬っている人かは分かんないよな
I can’t know if they fear Jehovah.
Let’s turn in our Bibles
to the book
テモテ第一 1章5節を開いて
読んでみましょう
of 1 Timothy 1:5
and notice how it reads:
何と書かれているでしょうか？
“Really, the objective of this instruction
“実際のところ
この指令が目ざしているものは—”
“is love out of a clean heart
“清い心と正しい良心と
偽善のない信仰とから出る愛です”
“and out of a good conscience
and out of faith without hypocrisy.”
聖書の原則から
エホバのお考えが分かります
We train our conscience
with Bible principles
that reveal Jehovah’s thinking.
その原則で
自分の良心を訓練するのです
There may be several principles needed
直面している問題に当てはまる原則が
幾つかあるでしょう
for our unique problem.
では それを見つけて当てはめましょう
But when we find
and apply them,
そうするなら 清い心
正しい良心を持てるのです
we’ll enjoy a clean heart
and a good conscience.
How did their Bible principles
and meditation
皆さんの考えと彼らが考えた原則を
比べていかがでしたか？
compare to what
you were thinking?
Now, you may not have come up
with the same scriptures and thoughts,
ひょっとしたら ビデオとは違う聖句や
考えだったかもしれませんが 大丈夫です
but that’s OK.
The important thing is that by training
our “power of reason,”
大切なのは—
“理性”を働かせ 自分の考えを
エホバのお考えと調和させることです
we’re aligning our thoughts
with Jehovah’s thoughts.
Did you see the three skills in use?
3つのスキルをどう使ったでしょうか？
The young brother was able
若い兄弟は隠れた危険を
思い描くことができました
to visualize his potential friends.
He couldn’t see them literally,
目には見えませんが—
but knowing they didn’t fear Jehovah
or keep His orders
エホバを恐れない人と
一緒にゲームをするのは—
良くない交わりだと
気づくことができました
painted a picture of the kind of associates
they might prove to be.
When our sister
analyzed 2 Timothy 2:16,
若い姉妹は
テモテ第二 2章16節を分析し—
she saw the social media comments
SNSでの会話が 信仰を弱めさせる
“むだ話”だと気付きました
were similar to “empty speeches”
that could weaken her faith.
And the family head balanced
家族の頭は マタイ 6章31節の—
his family responsibilities
思い煩ってはならないという原則を
適用することで—
by applying the principle
at Matthew 6:31,
家族の責任に対するバランスを
取ることができました
where Jesus said
not to be anxious over material things.
And we can imagine him trying
to work the matter out with his boss
この兄弟は
仕事を失うことになるとしても—
エホバが自分と家族を養ってくださると
信頼して—
while trusting Jehovah
to care for him and his family,
上司と話し合おうと
決心したことでしょう
no matter what
might happen to his job.
Think now about another principle
in Matthew chapter 6.
マタイ 6章から
別の原則を考えてみましょう
Jesus tells us in verse 33
to ‘seek first the Kingdom.’
イエスは 33節で
“王国を第一に求めなさい”と言われました
Young ones especially
face temptations
若い人は特に 多かれ少なかれ
世の事柄に誘惑されやすいものです
—both large and small—
to seek things
in the world instead.
And sadly, some have ignored
Bible principles they have learned.
悲しいことに
聖書の原則を無視した人もいます
They’ve looked
for happiness in what appears
この体制の見せかけの成功に
幸福を見いだそうとしました
to be the exciting possibilities
of this system of things.
In this “Truth Transforms Lives” segment,
「真理は人の生き方を変化させる」
のシリーズで—
Sister Anneliese Zelina explains
what led her to a similar choice
アンネリーゼ･ゼリーナ姉妹が
世に引き込まれた後—
and what drew her back to Jehovah.
エホバのもとに帰った経験について
語ります
Growing up in the truth,
真理のうちに育ちました
I felt like I fit in
でも 学校の友達とか世の人のほうが
わたしには合うなって思いました
more with my friends at school
or people who weren’t Witnesses.
I was living a double life
and I knew it.
裏表がありました
I was not baptized.
バプテスマはまだでした
I had always tried to make
the truth fit in with the world.
この世的な生き方をしても
真理のうちにいるつもりでした
And this time I decided
that I just want to give
ただ この世の生き方が
どんな感じか知りたかったんです
the world a shot
and see what that’s like.
I came right to my parents,
and I said,
両親に “ロサンゼルスに行って
モデルになる”って言いました
“I want to move to LA
and pursue modeling.”
1週間もせずに初めての仕事が
決まったんです
I had my first job within the week.
It looked so glamorous.
すっごく華やかです
There were a lot of parties
パーティーがたくさんありました
—going to the coolest houses,
getting to hang out with celebrities.
すてきな家に行って セレブと遊びました
There are no rules.
ルールなんてありません
You have the money
to do whatever you want.
なんでもできるお金もあります
That lifestyle was so far
from what I was raised knowing as right
それは 正しいと分かってたことから
かけ離れていました
実際 エホバとの関係は
全くありませんでした
that I basically had
no relationship with Jehovah.
Once all the smoke
and mirrors are gone,
初めの興奮が覚めると
本当のことが見えてきます
you see these things
for what they are.
I remember I called my mom,
母に電話で “ソドムとゴモラの
真ん中にいるみたい”って言いました
and I told her:
“It’s like Sodom and Gomorrah.
I’m literally in the middle of it all.”
最高なはずなのに
わたしは幸せじゃありません
And I thought, like, this is it;
this is what everyone says is the best,
and I’m not happy.
つまらないし むなしかったんです
And I just felt so dull
—empty.
“親がエホバの証人じゃなければ……”
And I actually thought to myself:
‘I wish—
I wish I was never raised a Witness.
“エホバの存在も 知らなきゃ
よかったのに”と思いました
I wish I never even knew Jehovah existed.’
There were certain nights
where I needed him.
エホバを必要としたときもありました
“祈って近づこう”としたけど
できませんでした
I was thinking,
‘Just pray; just go to him.’
And I couldn’t.
エホバのもとにはもう戻れない
と思いました
I thought I would never be able to
come back to Jehovah.
One of the jobs
I got hired to do
あるとき ファッション雑誌の
仕事をしました
was to work
for this young fashion company.
In between different outfits and shoots,
you would, you know,
スチール撮影の合間に
カメラマンと話しました
talk with the photographer.
So, what are you guys
going to be for Halloween?
ハロウィーンは仮装する？
Matt doesn’t celebrate Halloween.
彼はしないわ
エホバの証人だから
He’s one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
So am I.
わたしも
It’s not a joke.
冗談？
No, I’m not kidding.
わたしも親がエホバの証人なの
I was raised as a Witness.
あぁ ぼくもだ
Yeah, I was raised as one as well.
Do you, um—
do you go to meetings?
集会には……行ってる？
いや ずっと行ってない
No, I haven’t been in forever.
What about you?
そっちは？
全然 行ってない
No, no, I haven’t.
I got a last-minute job to New York.
急な仕事で ニューヨークに行きました
I decided to walk the Brooklyn Bridge.
ブルックリン橋を渡りました
I knew Bethel was there,
and I’d never been to Bethel.
ベテルには 行ったことありませんでした
This sister stopped me on my tour,
and she invited me up to her office.
ツアーの途中で
ある姉妹のオフィスに行きました
復活のいろんな絵がありました
There were different paintings
of the resurrection.
She asked me, “Do you know why
the people are waiting on the balcony?”
“なぜ みんなバルコニーで待ってる
と思う？”って聞かれて—
And I was like,
“I—I don’t know. Why?”
“さぁ なぜ？”って答えたら—
And she said, “Because they’re waiting
for their loved ones to be resurrected.”
“愛する人が復活してくるのを
待ってるからよ”って言われたんです
It was as if something
just went straight to my heart.
その言葉が心に響きました
そんなこと初めてです
I’ve never felt something like that.
I had for the first time actually seen
the resurrection and believed it.
復活を本当に理解して信じたのは
初めてでした
It wasn’t just this thing that might happen
—it was for sure.
起こるかも じゃなくて 確実なこと
I knew exactly
what it was going to look like.
どんな様子かはっきり分かりました
I would be standing there
on that balcony
わたしもバルコニーで—
looking for my loved ones
to come back,
自分の愛する人が帰ってくるのを
待ちたい—
and I wanted to be there.
そこにいたい……
The resurrection was so real to me.
復活がリアルになりました
And the second I got out of Bethel,
ベテルから出てすぐ 母に電話しました
I—I called my mom,
and I told her, and I said:
“ママ ママ わたし戻る”
“Mom, Mom, I’m coming back.
“I know exactly what I need to do.
“何をすべきかちゃんと分かったの”
I’m coming back to Jehovah.”
“エホバのもとに戻る”
I had made up my mind, you know,
I’m going to give Jehovah a chance.
エホバにお仕えしようと決めました
But, you know,
I’m coming back to the truth.
もう一度戻って やりなおそうと
思いました
I’m going to do it right.
There was an elder
who was doing the Watchtower,
ものみの塔の司会の兄弟は
とても親切そうでした
and he just came off so kind
that I thought, you know,
when this meeting ends,
それで 集会が終わったら—
あの兄弟に ここに来た理由を
言おうと思いました
I want to talk with him, and I’m going
to explain to him why I’m here.
I knew I had so many changes to make.
たくさん変化が必要です
Matthew 6:33 is so important to me,
マタイ 6章33節は大切です
‘Seek first the Kingdom.’
“王国を第一に求めなさい”
My entire life I sought
everything else before Jehovah.
これまで エホバではないものを
求めていました
エホバを第一にしていなかったんです
I never put him first,
and I for the first time was saying,
初めて “はい エホバ
あなたを第一にします”と言いました
“OK, Jehovah, I’m going to put you first.”
The job I have right now
isn’t necessarily my dream job,
今の仕事は
あこがれの仕事じゃありません
でも おかげでエホバのために
本当にしたい開拓奉仕ができるんです
but it allows me to do exactly
what I want to do for Jehovah
—and that’s pioneer.
I used to walk down Hollywood Boulevard
以前は ハリウッドの大通りを
モデルの仕事で奔走していましたけど—
going from casting to casting
with my portfolio in hand,
今は そこに立って
カートの奉仕をしています
and now I walk down Hollywood Boulevard
with the cart in my hand.
奉仕中 昔のモデル仲間に会うので
わたしの新しい生き方よ—
Out in the ministry,
I see models that I used to work with,
and I love getting to show
them that this is my new life,
これがわたしを変えたのって
教えています
and this has changed my life.
とっても幸せです
I am so happy.
I know what it’s like
to superficially feel good.
表面的に満足できることじゃなくて—
But to literally have the joy,
the happiness
本当の喜び 幸せを
みんなに伝えたいんです
—I want to share that with everybody.
Jehovah completely changed my life.
エホバのおかげです
We’re so happy
that Sister Zelina returned
ゼリーナ姉妹がエホバのもとに帰り
献身したことを嬉しく思います
and dedicated
her life to Jehovah.
Even though she wanted to forget
what she knew about God,
姉妹は神について学んだことを
忘れたいと思っていましたが—
the things she had learned about him
kept coming back to her mind.
学んだことが心の中に
よみがえってきました
Finally, when she saw
the picture of the resurrection,
そして ベテルを見学して
復活の絵を見た時—
while touring Bethel,
エホバの愛が姉妹を強くとらえました
it was a powerful reminder
of Jehovah’s love.
Really,
Sister Zelina’s Bible-trained conscience
姉妹の聖書によって訓練された良心は
確かに良い影響を与えました
was at work the entire time.
Young ones, please know
that Jehovah does not want
若い皆さん エホバは決して皆さんに
楽しみ事をあきらめさせたいわけでも—
to hold you back
from having fun,
才能を用いて生活を楽しむのが—
and he doesn’t want
you to feel guilty
悪いことだと思わせたいのでも
ありません
for the desire to use
your talents and to enjoy life.
But he does want to protect you
from spiritual dangers,
エホバはあなたを霊的な危険から
守りたいと思っておられ—
and he asks you to seek first
the Kingdom in these last days.
この終わりの日に王国を求めるよう
願っておられるのです
Proverbs 10:22 puts it well:
箴言 10章22節にあるとおりです
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
that makes one rich,
“エホバの祝福
それが人を富ませるのであり—”
and He adds no pain with it.”
“神はそれに痛みを加えられない”
It is Satan’s system that adds
any pain we may experience.
わたしたちが経験する痛みは
すべてサタンの体制によるものです
Sister Zelina and so many others
have found that scripture to be true.
ゼリーナ姉妹や大勢の兄弟姉妹は
この聖句が真実だと確信しています
So often, young ones who choose
to give Jehovah their best
エホバにすべてを差し出すことにした
若い人たちは—
聖なる奉仕において自分の才能や能力を
用いることによって祝福されています
are blessed with ways to use
their talents and interests
in sacred service.
Jehovah wants you to be part
エホバは ミカ 4章2節の
素晴らしい成就に—
of the exciting fulfillment
of Micah 4:2,
あなたにも加わってほしいと
願っておられます
where nations are saying:
“Come, let us go up
to the mountain of Jehovah.”
“来なさい エホバの山に上ろう”
Well, that verse was the daily text
この聖句に関して 最近の朝の崇拝で—
and part of a morning worship discussion
ジェフリー･ジャクソン兄弟が
話をしてくださいました
by Brother Geoffrey Jackson.
Micah’s prophecy is being fulfilled now,
ミカの預言は 現在成就しており
世界的な兄弟関係の実現と—
and it results
in our worldwide brotherhood
and highlights the need
for Christian unity and neutrality.
クリスチャンの一致と中立の必要性を
強調しています
So Brother Jackson asked
an interesting question,
ジャクソン兄弟が—
「中立がそれほど重要なのはなぜか？」
という興味深い話をしてくださいました
“How important is our neutrality?”
It’s true, isn’t it?
When we look at this prophecy
in the book of Micah,
ミカ書は興奮を誘います
it’s very exciting
because it portrays to us
その預言が 現在 神の民の間で
生じていることを描いているからです
what’s actually happening
among God’s people today.
We know that although
in the new world
新しい世で 神の民の間に—
素晴らしい一致が見られるということを
わたしたちは知っていますが—
there will be a tremendous unity
displayed by God’s people,
chapter 4 of Micah
ミカ 4章は まさに今 起きていて—
is actually portraying  what’s happening now,
わたしたちにもかかわりのあることを
描いています
and we’re involved with this.
We know that because
in verse 5 it says
5節には その一致と同時に
存在する状況について—
that at the same time
that this unity would be evident:
“All the peoples will walk,
each in the name of its god.”
“もろもろの民は皆—”
“それぞれ自分たちの神の名によって歩む”
とあるからです
Well, that’s not talking
about the new world, is it?
It’s talking about the time
we are living in now.
これは新しい世には当てはまりません
今の時代のことを言っていますね
Well, what is it that helps all
of Jehovah’s Witnesses worldwide
世界中のエホバの証人を
これほどまでに一致させ—
to be so united and not to be involved
with the wars of this world?
世の紛争にかかわらないように
させているものは何でしょうか？
Well, one of the things that helps us
is our Christian neutrality.
1つは クリスチャンの中立の立場です
What do we mean by neutrality?
中立とは何でしょうか？
We mean not taking sides
in political issues.
政治問題において
いずれの側にも付かないということです
Of course, we take sides
with Jehovah and the Kingdom,
エホバとその王国は支持しますが—
but with regard to worldly political debates
and issues that arise,
世の政治論争や政治問題に関しては
どちらの側も支持しないのです
we don’t take sides.
Why is this so important?
それが重要なのはなぜでしょうか？
Well, let’s turn our Bibles
to Revelation chapter 13.
啓示 13章を開きましょう
Revelation 13:16, 17,
13章 16, 17節です
and here it tells us:
“それは すべての人 すなわち
小なる者と大なる者—”
“It puts under compulsion all people
—the small and the great,
“the rich and the poor,
the free and the slaves
“富んだ者と貧しい者
自由な者と奴隷を強制して—”
“—that these should be marked
on their right hand or on their forehead,
“その右手や額に印を受けさせ—”
“and that nobody can buy or sell
except a person having the mark,
“また その印 つまり野獣の名—”
“もしくはその名の数字を
持つ者以外には—”
the name of the wild beast
or the number of its name.”
“だれも売り買いできないようにする”
What’s the point of this verse?
この聖句の要点は何でしょうか？
Well, of course,
we will look forward to seeing
この聖句がどのように成就するか—
how this may
turn out in the future
神の民に
どんな圧力がかかってくるかは—
and what pressure is put
on God’s people at that time.
将来明らかになるでしょう
But even now,
we see the principle here
しかし 今でさえ
政治体制がわたしたちに—
that the political system is wanting
to put its mark on us,
印を付けたがっている
ということは明らかです
mentally as well as physically.
行動においても 考えにおいてもです
So we see the forehead
as well as the hand being involved.
“右手や額に”
と言われているからです
So we need to be absolutely certain
that we remain neutral
ですから わたしたちは 政治に
直接関与しないのはもちろんのこと—
with regard to political issues
in the world,
not only by
not being involved actively
気持ちの上でもどちらかの側に
付くことのないようにして—
in the political issues
中立を保つよう
注意深くあるべきです
but also mentally not allowing
ourselves to take sides.
What are some of the things
that perhaps could erode our neutrality?
わたしたちの中立が徐々に崩れていく
ということもあります
Well, maybe we could mention
three things this morning.
今日は３つの原因を考えましょう
One is the propaganda
that the world puts forward.
最初に この世のプロパガンダ
—宣伝— です
Now, we have seen what the media says
about Jehovah’s Witnesses, haven’t we?
時々メディアが
ゆがめられた報道をするため—
How distorted some of their reports are
人々はエホバの証人に対し
マイナスのイメージを持つようになります
and how they can paint
a negative picture with regard to us.
Well, should we expect
that they are neutral
他の報道に関しても同じことが
あり得るのではないでしょうか？
with regard to other events
that they report on,
particularly when there are conflicts
between two nations?
二国間が対立している場合は
特にそう言えます
The media
in one particular nation may promote
一方の国のメディアは相手国に関して—
certain ideas about the other nation.
ある種のイメージを持たせようと
するかもしれません
We may be affected by that.
We may be surprised perhaps
政治イデオロギーの異なる国を
実際に旅行してみると—
to visit some other countries
that have a different political ideology
メディアが報道していたものと
実際の様子が違うことに—
and be surprised to see
how things perhaps are a little different
驚くことがあります
in that country to how it’s portrayed
by the media in our country.
So we need to be careful
not to be influenced
ですから 世の宣伝
特にメディアの報道に—
by the propaganda of this world,
簡単に影響されないよう
注意する必要があります
particularly media reports and so on.
What’s another thing perhaps
that could cause us
中立の立場を危うくさせる
別の要素を考えましょう
to lose a measure of neutrality?
Sporting events.
スポーツイベントです
Sometimes sporting events
are able to achieve
スポーツイベントは人々の間に
国家主義をあおることがあります
certain goals
with regard to nationalism.
多くのスポーツイベントでは
国歌が歌われます
We see the national anthem
being played at many of these events.
何年も前のこと
別の国にいた時—
It reminds me many years ago
when I was in a different country,
友人がわたしにスポーツイベントを
録画してほしいと頼んできました
a friend of mine asked me
to record a certain sporting event.
あまり関心はなかったのですが—
I wasn’t particularly
interested in the event,
友人の頼みでしたので 録画しました
but because he made this request,
I recorded it.
特に 最後の10分は—
確実に録画できるよう
慎重に行ないました
And, of course, I wanted to make sure
that I got the last ten minutes of it.
その部分を録画し損なって—
I thought our friendship
may be strained
友情にひびが入っては大変だ
と思ったからです
if I didn’t get
the actual last part of the game.
それで
観戦することになったのですが—
When I watched it,
it was absolutely exciting
これが大変エキサイティングで
スリリングな終盤でした
—nail-biting finish.
Well, after the brother
gave me back the videotape,
彼がビデオテープを
返してくれた時に—
I thought maybe
some of the other brothers
このイベントが好きな他の兄弟も
見たいかもしれないと思い—
who would be interested
in this sporting event
テープは消去せず 何人かに
見たいかどうか尋ねてみました
may want to have it
rather than just wipe the tape.
So I offered it to several,
and each one of them said to me:
ところが皆 “いや やめとくよ—”
“No thanks.
“うちが勝ったんだったら
見てもいいけど” と言いました
If we had won,
perhaps it would be different.”
Now, what was the problem?
わたしはこう聞きました
As I said to them,
“観戦するのはプレーを楽しむため？
それともどちらかを応援するため？”
“Were you watching the game
or were you taking sides?”
An interesting concept,
というのは このゲームでは—
because here
two different nations were involved.
2つのナショナルチームが
戦っていたからです
So we have to be careful
that even sporting events
ですから スポーツ観戦であっても—
国家主義的な感情が
わき上がることのないように—
don’t stir up within us
certain nationalistic feelings,
注意する必要があります
and perhaps we could take sides
with regard to certain events.
自国を応援してしまうというのは
あり得ることだからです
The third area that perhaps
could erode our neutrality:
中立の立場を崩されかねない
3つ目の分野は—
the political promises being made,
particularly at election time.
政治家のする約束—
特に選挙時の公約です
Perhaps one of the candidates
is from our ethnic background
自分と同じ民族の人や—
自分と同性の人が
立候補するかもしれません
or perhaps
is the same gender as we are.
When we look at the political situation
these days with many elections,
最近の選挙は 政治というよりは
エンターテイメントという感じです
it seems to be more in the form
of entertainment than anything else,
with music
and very colorful characters.
音楽やカラフルなマスコットが
目立ちます
But if we were
to say in our heart,
心の中で
“こんな人に当選してほしくないな”—
‘I hope that idiot
doesn’t get into power,’
などと思い始めたとしたら—
are we neutral?
それは中立と言えるでしょうか？
Or worse still, if we say,
もっと悪いことに
“あの人が当選したらいいのに”—
‘I hope the other person
gets into power,’
などと思い始めたら大変です
well, we need
to be careful, don’t we?
I remember many years ago
as a young pioneer in Australia,
わたしは若い頃 オーストラリアで
開拓奉仕をしていましたが—
I was facing
the conscription issue
徴兵の問題に直面しました
—the national call-up
for the military.
At that time,
the Vietnam War was being fought.
ベトナム戦争の真っただ中でした
And then there was
an election in Australia.
時を同じくして
オーストラリアでは選挙がありました
And at that time, the party
that was trying to get into power
当時 政権を取ろうとしていた政党が
徴兵廃止を公約に掲げていました
said that if they got into power,
they would abolish conscription.
So now that affected me personally.
わたしも個人的に影響を受けました
I remember how hard it was sitting there
watching the election results,
選挙結果を見ながら—
その政党に勝ってほしい
という気持ちを抑えるのは大変でした
not to say in my heart,
‘I hope they get in.’
And then, when they got in,
not to say, ‘Yes!’
実際 その政党が政権を取った時には
やった！と言いそうになりました
You see, if we personally are affected
by some of these political promises,
このように政治公約を
気持ちの上で支持してしまうなら—
we may violate our neutrality.
中立ではいられなくなります
So brothers and sisters,
let’s work hard at remembering
それでは 兄弟たち—
わたしたちはこの世のものではないことを
しっかりと銘記しましょう
that we’re no part of this world.
We support the best government
that could ever rule this earth.
わたしたちが支持する政府は—
最善の仕方で
この地を支配することができるのです
And by doing so,
we will keep our neutrality,
そのようにして 中立を保ち
一致を保っていきましょう
and we will keep our unity.
When neutrality is mentioned,
中立について言われると いつも
戦争のことを思い浮かべませんか？
isn’t it true we often think of taking
a stand during times of war?
But Brother Jackson
reminded us that neutrality
しかし ジャクソン兄弟は—
わたしたちの毎日の会話や思考において
中立を保つよう勧めてくれました
is something we do every day
in our thoughts and in our speech.
What a good example
of analyzing a Bible principle
聖書の原則を 分析して
正しく理解し 適用する点で—
to understand its full meaning
and application for us.
なんと素晴らしい実例でしょう
Of course,
there are times when governments
もちろん 政府が
神の民の信仰を捨てさせ—
do pressure God’s people
to renounce their faith or take up arms.
武器を取るよう
圧力をかけるときがあります
This happened
to Sister Gertrud Pötzinger
このことは第二次大戦中
ナチ・ドイツで—
and her husband, Martin,
ゲルトルート･ポエツィンガー姉妹と
夫のマーティン兄弟にふりかかりました
in Nazi Germany
during World War II.
Now, later in life, Brother Pötzinger
was a member of the Governing Body,
後に ポエツィンガー兄弟は
統治体のメンバーになり—
and he finished
his earthly course in 1988;
1988年に
地上での歩みを終えましたが—
but Sister Pötzinger continued
faithful until her death in 2003.
姉妹は2003年に亡くなるまで
忠実を保たれました
In an archived interview,
アーカイブのビデオで
姉妹は戦時中の経験を語っておられます
Sister Pötzinger described
her wartime experiences.
恐ろしい迫害の中で
兄弟姉妹はどのように—
How did Gertrud and Martin,
like thousands
of our spiritual brothers and sisters,
他の大勢の兄弟たちと
同じように忠実を保ったでしょうか？
keep their integrity
through brutal persecution?
I worked underground
and traveled in Silesia,
わたしはシュレジエン州で
地下活動に携わりました
and at that time,
I visited the families
with copies of The Watchtower.
「ものみの塔」誌のコピーを持って
家族を訪ねた際に—
They caught me and arrested me
ドレスデンで逮捕されました
in Dresden.
And there, there was
the same strong interrogation,
厳しい尋問を受けましたが—
エホバは素晴らしい仕方で
助けてくださいました
and Jehovah helped me
in a wonderful way.
I was surprised by myself
自分でも驚くような返答ができたんです
こう尋問されました
—what kind of thoughts
came in my mind
when they asked me,
“ものみの塔の組織の活動が—”
“Did you know
“政府に禁止されていることを
知らないのか？”
“that the organization
of the Watchtower
is forbidden
by the government?”
“もちろん 知っています”
と答えました
I was saying,
“Sure, I know that.”
“Why were you
working underground
“なぜ 命令に反して地下活動を
行なっていたんだ？” と言われました
against our command?”
Then I was saying:
わたしは こう答えました
“The German judgment,
“ドイツの裁判所は
「盗んではならない」—”
“they acknowledge the command:
“「偽ってはならない」—”
“「殺人をしてはならない」
といった命令に従っています”
“‘You have not to steal,
not to lie, not to murder.’
“And this came from the Mosaic Law;
it’s from the Bible.
“それらの命令は 聖書にある
モーセの律法から取られています”
“If you acknowledge
this command,
“それらの命令に従うのであれば—”
“then you have to acknowledge
the other command too.
“律法の他の命令にも従うべき
ではないでしょうか？”
“The Bible is saying:
‘You have to watch
“聖書は「集まり合い 互いに
励まし合うように」と命令しています”
“to come together
and to encourage one another.’
“How can I do it
if I would be ashamed to meet them?
“禁令を恐れていては
この命令に従うことはできないんです”
“I want to do the will of God.
“わたしは神のご意志に従いたいと
思っています”
This is a commandment.”
The judge was saying nothing.
“これは明確な命令です”
He spoke with the side judge,
but he gave no answer.
裁判官たちは お互いに何か
言い合っていましたが—
I was sentenced
at first for five years.
わたしには何も言いませんでした
And later on,
5年の刑を言い渡されて—
they made it go down
to three and a half years
後に3年半に減刑されました
まだ若かったからです
because I was so young;
I was 25 years of age.
25歳でした
So I started
my solitary confinement.
独房での生活が始まりました
But Jehovah’s spirit
made me real joyful.
わたしはエホバの霊のおかげで
喜びに満たされていました
Every day
I was thinking:
“毎日 特定の事について
思い巡らすようにしよう” と考えました
‘Now I have
to make every day
‘a special object
to think about.
‘In fact,
I want to think
それで エホバの特質を選びました
about the qualities
of Jehovah.
最初は知恵です
I’ll start with wisdom.’
外の騒音が聞こえないように
指で耳をふさいで—
And so I put
my fingers in my ears
部屋の中を行ったり来たりしながら
黙想しました
and was running
to and fro and to and fro.
I wanted
to hear nothing outside.
思いが素晴らしいもので
満たされていたので 幸せでした
So, wonderful thoughts
and I was happy.
Then when that was over,
エホバの特質の次に—
then I thought:
‘What is hope?
“希望とは何か？”
“信仰とは？”
What is faith?’
それらの霊の実について考えました
I started to think
about the fruits of the spirit.
You have a lot.
考えることはいくらでもあったので—
Then I have
so much to think,
あっという間に
時間が過ぎていきました
and the time runs.
After three and a half years,
3年半が過ぎると—
the Gestapo
called me again
ゲシュタポから宣言書を渡されました
and gave me
a declaration.
I have to sign
エホバの証人と関係を断ち—
that I never want
to be in connection
聖書も学ばないという宣言書に—
with the Jehovah’s Witnesses
and that I refuse
署名するよう言われました
to learn more
from the Bible.
“絶対に署名しません”
と答えました
And I said:
“No! Never!”
Then he said,
“You can think for overnight.”
一晩 考えるよう言われたので
即答しました
“No!
I want not to think overnight.”
“その必要はありません
署名は絶対にいたしません”
And immediately I said:
“Never will I do it!
Never will I sign it!”
するとこう言われました
“それならば仕方ない—”
And then he was saying:
“お前をラベンスブリュックの
強制収容所に送ることにする”
“Then you have
to take the consequences.
“You will transfer
to the concentration camp
—to Ravensbruck.”
And when I came,
到着すると 服をすべて脱がされ
取り上げられました
they ordered that I have
to put all my dress out
and to get them away.
他の囚人と一緒に 大きな部屋で
何時間も待たされました
And then I have to stay
with other prisoners
several hours
in a big bedroom.
その後 医師の診察を受けさせられました
And we have to wait
till the doctor will see us.
とても屈辱的でした
And it was
so humiliating.
恥をかかせて 惨めな思いにさせるのが
彼らの目的でした
They wanted to humiliate,
and they wanted
to make us down.
若い女性も 年配の女性もいました
And the old women
between the young girls,
みんな 屈辱的な思いをしました
they were  so strongly ashamed.
You saw it
—how they suffered.
そこには 苦悩が満ちていました
I never will forget this.
忘れられません
And after,
その後 囚人服をあてがわれ—
we got the new dress
from the camp
懲罰バラックに送られました
and we were assigned to go
to the punishment barrack.
And then
that was a terrible night.
それは凄惨な夜でした
So many prisoners,
大勢の囚人が 一晩中
泣いたり吐いたりしていました
they were crying the night
and others were vomiting
ひどかったです
—had to vomit.
翌日から 強制労働が始まりました
It was a terrible night.
The next day,
we had to go for working.
夏は 朝5時に点呼があり—
We had so strong to work
夜7時まで
厳しい労働をさせられました
from morning
—in summertime,
from 5 o’clock
we were on the roll call place
till evening, 7 o’clock.
Then the quarantine came.
ある時 検疫官が来て
バラックから出ないように言われました
We have to not go out.
They closed the door.
They gave us our meals
through the window,
食事は窓越しに与えられました
それは 思ってもみなかった休息と
なりました
and we had
a fine time to have rest.
We encouraged one another
with spiritual interests.
霊的な事を話し合って
励まし合いました
And the doctor came
and knocked on the window.
医者が来て—
“このバラックで死んだ者はいるか？”
“Who died in your barrack?”
“Nobody.”
“だれも！”
No one.
“一人も 死んでいません！”
Our old, weak sisters
they overcame all.
年配のか弱い姉妹たちでさえ
生き残ったんです
Never some became sick.
病気にさえなりませんでした
So it was really a good witness
それは 収容所内で
とても良い証言になりました
for the others in the camp.
My husband was
in the concentration camp,
主人は ダハウの後には
マウトハウゼンの強制収容所にいました
at first in Dachau
and later on in Mauthausen.
主人たちは
石切り場で働かされました
They worked
in the stone quarry.
And in that group,
ある兄弟は 靴がきつかったので—
a brother
had the bad shoes;
それを石切り場で脱いだのですが—
they were too tight for him,
and he took them off.
収容所に持って帰るのを
忘れてしまいました
And he had forgotten
to take them from the stone quarry
to the camp.
主人は靴を取ってきてあげようと
駆け出していきました
And my husband
wanted to help him,
and he was running
to pick up the shoes.
監視員は 主人が他の囚人たちから
離れたのを見て—
And the watchman
observed that he
ran away from the lawn,
from the group.
罰として主人を
杭に1時間つるしたんです
His punishment was to hang
for one hour on the pole.
わたしは主人に聞きました
“よく耐えられたわね”
When I asked my husband,
“How did you overcome
such a torture?”
主人はこう答えました
“アブラハムのことを考えていたんだ”
Then he said:
“I was thinking:
“‘How was the situation
“息子をささげるために
長距離を歩いて行った時—”
“‘when Abraham
had to kill his son?
“アブラハムは
何を考えていたんだろうって”
“And this was a long way.’
“I was always thinking:
“どうやって自分の気持ちに
打ち勝てたのか—”
“‘What were his thoughts?
“‘How had he
overcome his feeling
“エホバは彼に
何を期待しておられたのか”
and what Jehovah
wants for him?’”
そんなことを考えていたら
痛みを感じなくなったそうです
And in this way,
he didn’t feel anymore.
1時間後 杭から降ろされた主人を見て
兄弟たちが言ったそうです
After one hour,
when he came down,
the other brothers
were saying,
“You don’t look as you have been
on the torture stake.”
“苦しみの杭から下りてきた人には
全く見えないね”
So Jehovah can help us
エホバはどんな状況にあっても
助けることがおできになるんです
in all such situations.
Every situation we had some
大変な状況もあるでしょう
of what was not so easy.
でも どんな状況下でも—
But in every situation,
エホバの霊という素晴らしい助けを
実感できるのです
we have a touch of wonderful help
—Jehovah’s spirit.
And we could pray.
そして 祈りもあります
Jehovah’s name
is the most important part in our life.
エホバのみ名
それは人生で一番重要なものです
Nothing is so important
like Jehovah’s name.
それ以上のものはありません
Did you see the ways Jehovah blessed
Sister Pötzinger’s determination
圧力のもとで忠誠を保とう
という姉妹の決意を—
エホバがどのように祝福されたか
お気づきですか？
to stay loyal under pressure?
At Matthew 10:19,
Jesus told his apostles:
マタイ 10章19節でイエスは
“人々があなた方を引き渡すとき—”
“When they hand you over,
do not become anxious
“どのように または何を話そうかと
思い煩ってはなりません”
“about how or what
you are to speak,
“話すべきことはその時あなた方に
与えられるからです”と言われました
for what you are to speak
will be given you in that hour.”
逮捕され 尋問を受けていた時—
She may have felt that same assurance
姉妹にも
同様の確信があったことでしょう
when arrested and interrogated.
Then, when tested in the camps,
収容所にいた間
姉妹とマーティン兄弟は—
she and Martin meditated
on Christian qualities
クリスチャンの特質と聖書中の
信仰の手本について黙想しました
and the faith of Bible characters.
And finally they,
最終的に 多くの信仰の仲間と同様に—
like so many Witnesses,
were helped to survive
because of the love and care
霊的な兄弟姉妹の愛と世話によって
生き延びることができました
of their spiritual brothers and sisters.
Sister Pötzinger used her experience
ポエツィンガー姉妹はご自分の経験を
話して他の人を励ましました
to encourage others
in her later assignments.
For example, in the interview
例えば マレンフォント兄弟姉妹への
インタビューの中で—
with William and Sandra Malenfant,
マレンフォント姉妹は
ベテルの裁縫部門で共に奉仕した—
Sister Malenfant remembered working
with Sister Pötzinger
in the Bethel Sewing Department,
ポエツィンガー姉妹が 印象的な例えを
語られたことを話していました
and Sister Pötzinger had given her
a memorable sewing illustration.
She likened each prayer
to adding another thread
姉妹は 一つ一つの祈りが
エホバとわたしたちをつなぐ糸になり—
to a strong cord
that unites us with Jehovah.
それが合わさって
強い綱になると話されました
You might enjoy
watching that interview again
このインタビューは
「経験とインタビュー」のセクションの—
in the “Interviews and Experiences” section,
「神聖な奉仕の祝福」
でご覧いただけます
under “Blessings of Sacred Service.”
Later this month,
you’ll also want to watch
今月後半
「音楽」のセクションから—
a new original song
under the “Music” section.
新しいオリジナルソングを
お楽しみいただけます
In the April 2016 program,
2016年4月のプログラムで—
a group of young ones explained
若い人たちがベテルを見学し
そこで見た思い出について語りました
why they visited Bethel
and what they enjoyed seeing.
While there, they also sang
a song about their experience,
このオリジナルソングでは—
子どもたちが訪問した支部で
ベテル奉仕者と一緒に歌っています
with the help of Bethelites,
at the branches they visited.
And we have a music video
to enjoy in this month’s program.
今月のミュージックビデオを
ご覧ください
It’s called
Stop, Think, and Pray.
タイトルは「悩むのをやめて」です
No matter what the problem is,
わたしたちに何が起きるとしても
いつも時間をかけて聖書の原則を考え—
we should always take time
to think about Bible principles
エホバの聖霊を
祈り求めなければなりません
and pray for Jehovah’s holy spirit.
騒がしい 友達に
Life’s not easy when trouble’s around
And the whole situation is getting you down.
今日も へこみそうになる
もしも誰かに気持ちを
So-called friends, they just want a reaction.
Turn to Jehovah and pray—
伝えられたら
気持ちを
Silently pray.
君を 見てる
Don’t give up; don’t give in.
Put your trust in Jehovah.
エホバ 信じて
あきらめないで
Keep it calm; we can win
If we stop, think, and pray.
強くなれる
空を ごらん
When there seems no way out,
He’ll be there, always by our side.
いつも そばにいるよ
悩むのを やめて
He will be our guide, never doubt;
No, just stop, think, and pray.
祈ろう 静かに
エホバ 今
Make Jehovah smile.
Let him show the way.
ほほ笑んでる
降り積もる トラブル
Ev’ry day will have troubles to share.
また今日も
There are bills to be paid
with no money to spare.
埋もれそうになる
もしも誰かに 笑顔を
Even so, we’ll be happy in giving
If we can make someone smile—
届けられたら
笑顔を
Make someone smile.
君を 守る
Never doubt; never fear.
Put your trust in Jehovah.
エホバ 信じて
And our road will be clear
If we stop, think, and pray.
恐れないで
道は ひらく
弱い時も
When we’re weak, we are strong.
And we’ll see he was by our side.
この手に 力がある
悩むのを やめて
He has been our guide all along.
Always stop, think, and pray.
祈ろう 静かに
エホバ 今
Make Jehovah smile.
Let him show the way.
ほほ笑んでる
エホバ 信じて
Put your trust in Jehovah.
And our road will be clear
思い出して
越えてゆける
If we stop, think, and pray.
When we’re weak, we are strong.
弱い時も
この手に 力がある
And we’ll see he was by our side.
He has been our guide all along.
悩むのを やめて
Always stop, think, and pray.
Make Jehovah smile.
祈ろう 静かに
エホバ 今
ほほ笑んでる
Thank him ev’ry day.
Jehovah will always bless us
悩みがあっても
エホバに祈りで近づく時—
when we go to him
in prayer with our concerns.
エホバはいつでも
祝福してくださいます
Whatever the situation,
どんな状況であっても エホバは
“普通を超えた力”を与えてくださいます
he can give us
“the power beyond what is normal.”
And as we learned
and practiced in this program,
今月のプログラムで考えたように—
we do our part by training
our “power of reason”
神の書の原則を用いて
“理性”を働かせていきましょう
with the principles
from his written Word.
Finally,
we have greetings
終わりに ノルウェーの
ベステルオーレン諸島の—
from the Vesterålen islands,
in Norway.
兄弟姉妹たちからのあいさつを
お送りします
These islands are home to 30,000 people
島々の人口は3万人で—
who enjoy the beautiful fjords, mountains,
美しいフィヨルドと山
穏やかなビーチに恵まれています
and calm beaches.
The 53 publishers
in the Sortland Norwegian Congregation
ソートランドノルウェー語会衆の
53人の伝道者が—
preach in a territory that covers
1,800 square kilometers,
1800平方キロに及ぶ区域を
奉仕しています
or 695 square miles.
Their thorough witnessing takes them
into the beautiful countryside,
徹底的な奉仕が
田舎の区域でも—
また ソートランドにおける
大都市の公の証言でもなされています
as well as to the city of Sortland
for metropolitan public witnessing.
毎年 未割り当て区域の
奉仕が計画され—
Each year, they organize trips
to unassigned territory,
where they often meet people
聖書に深い敬意を持つ人たちを
たくさん見いだしています
who show deep respect for the Bible.
毎月 土曜日の奉仕の後に
みんなで集まって—
One Saturday each month,
after the ministry,
they gather to watch
the JW Broadcasting program
JW Broadcastingを見ながら
楽しく過ごしています
and enjoy spending time together.
Progressive Bible studies
and a Russian group
進歩的な研究生やロシア語の群れが
毎週 集会に交わっています
join them each week
at their meetings.
We send our love
and greetings
わたしたちも
愛とあいさつを送り—
and thank them
for their Christian love
彼らのクリスチャン愛と信仰の手本に
感謝いたします
and example of faith.
Thank you for watching.
ご覧いただき
ありがとうございました
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcastingでした！
this is JW Broadcasting!